<?xml version="1.0" encoding="US-ASCII"?>
<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM "rfc2629.dtd">
<?rfc toc="yes"?>
<?rfc tocompact="yes"?>
<?rfc tocdepth="3"?>
<?rfc tocindent="yes"?>
<?rfc symrefs="yes"?>
<?rfc sortrefs="yes"?>
<?rfc comments="yes"?>
<?rfc inline="yes"?>
<?rfc compact="yes"?>
<?rfc subcompact="no"?>
<rfc category="info" docName="draft-fz-ippm-alt-mark-deployment-01"
     ipr="trust200902">
  <front>
    <title abbrev="enhanced-alternate-marking">Alternate Marking Deployment
    Framework</title>

    <author fullname="Giuseppe Fioccola" initials="G." surname="Fioccola">
      <organization>Huawei</organization>

      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>Palazzo Verrocchio, Centro Direzionale Milano 2</street>

          <city>Segrate (Milan)</city>

          <region/>

          <code>20054</code>

          <country>Italy</country>
        </postal>

        <email>giuseppe.fioccola@huawei.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <author fullname="Tianran Zhou" initials="T." surname="Zhou">
      <organization>Huawei</organization>

      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>156 Beiqing Rd.</street>

          <city>Beijing</city>

          <code>100095</code>

          <region/>

          <country>China</country>
        </postal>

        <email>zhoutianran@huawei.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <author fullname="Thomas Graf" initials="T." surname="Graf">
      <organization>Swisscom</organization>

      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>Binzring 17</street>

          <city>Zurich</city>

          <code>CH-8045</code>

          <region/>

          <country>Switzerland</country>
        </postal>

        <email>thomas.graf@swisscom.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <author fullname="Fabrizio Milan" initials="F." surname="Milan">
      <organization>TIM</organization>

      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>Via Reiss Romoli, 274</street>

          <city>Torino</city>

          <region/>

          <code>10148</code>

          <country>Italy</country>
        </postal>

        <email>fabrizio.milan@telecomitalia.it</email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <author fullname="Massimo Nilo" initials="M." surname="Nilo">
      <organization>TIM</organization>

      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>Via Reiss Romoli, 274</street>

          <city>Torino</city>

          <region/>

          <code>10148</code>

          <country>Italy</country>
        </postal>

        <email>massimo.nilo@telecomitalia.it</email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <author fullname="Keyi Zhu" initials="K." surname="Zhu">
      <organization>Huawei</organization>

      <address>
        <postal>
          <street/>

          <city/>

          <code/>

          <region/>

          <country/>
        </postal>

        <email>zhukeyi@huawei.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <author fullname="Lin Zhang" initials="L." surname="Zhang">
      <organization>China Mobile</organization>

      <address>
        <postal>
          <street/>

          <city/>

          <code/>

          <region/>

          <country/>
        </postal>

        <email>zhanglin1@cmdi.chinamobile.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <date day="25" month="September" year="2023"/>

    <workgroup>IPPM</workgroup>

    <abstract>
      <t>This document provides a framework for Alternate Marking deployment
      and includes considerations and guidance for the deployment of the
      methodology.</t>
    </abstract>
  </front>

  <middle>
    <section title="Introduction">
      <t>The <xref target="RFC9341">Alternate Marking</xref> and <xref
      target="RFC9342">Multipoint Alternate Marking</xref> define the
      Alternate Marking technique that is a hybrid performance measurement
      method, per <xref target="RFC7799"/> classification of measurement
      methods. This method is based on marking consecutive batches of packets
      and it can be used to measure packet loss, latency, and jitter on live
      traffic.</t>

      <t>The first experiments on Alternate-Marking are described in <xref
      target="RFC8321"/> and <xref target="RFC8889"/>.</t>

      <t>According to the definitions of <xref target="RFC7799"/>, the
      Alternate-Marking Method can be classified as Hybrid Type I. Indeed,
      Alternate Marking can be implemented by using reserved bits in the
      protocol header, and the change in value of these marking bits at the
      source node is formally considered a modification of the stream of
      interest.</t>

      <t>This document complements <xref target="RFC9341"/> and <xref
      target="RFC9342"/> as it explains the mechanisms that can be used to
      manage and deploy the method.</t>

      <section title="Requirements Language">
        <t>The key words "MUST", "MUST NOT", "REQUIRED", "SHALL", "SHALL NOT",
        "SHOULD", "SHOULD NOT", "RECOMMENDED", "NOT RECOMMENDED", "MAY", and
        "OPTIONAL" in this document are to be interpreted as described in BCP
        14 <xref target="RFC2119"/> <xref target="RFC8174"/> when, and only
        when, they appear in all capitals, as shown here.</t>
      </section>

      <section title="Terminology">
        <t>Abbreviations used in this document:<list>
            <t>AltMark: Alternate-Marking</t>

            <t>NMS: Network Management System</t>

            <t>IPv6: Internet Protocol version 6</t>

            <t>SRv6: Segment Routing over IPv6 dataplane</t>

            <t>BIER: Bit Index Explicit Replication</t>

            <t>MPLS: Multi-Protocol Label Switching</t>

            <t>SFC: Service Function Chaining</t>

            <t>NVO3: Network Virtualization Overlays</t>

            <t>IPFIX: IP Flow Information Export</t>

            <t>YANG: Yet Another Next Generation</t>

            <t>PCEP: Path Computation Element Communication Protocol</t>

            <t>BGP: Border Gateway Protocol</t>
          </list></t>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section title="Alternate Marking Deployment Domain">
      <t>The Alternate Marking Method MUST be deployed in a controlled domain
      for security and compatibility reasons. In this regard, <xref
      target="RFC8799"/> reports further examples of specific limited domain
      solutions. It is not common that the user traffic originates and
      terminates within the controlled domain. For this reason, it will
      typically only be applicable in an overlay network, where user traffic
      is encapsulated at one domain border, decapsulated at the other domain
      border and the encapsulation incorporates the relevant extension header
      for Alternate Marking. This requirement also implies that an
      implementation MUST filter packets that carry Alternate Marking data and
      are entering or leaving the controlled domain.</t>

      <t>A controlled domain is a managed network where it is required to
      select, monitor and control the access to the network by enforcing
      policies at the domain boundaries in order to discard undesired external
      packets entering the domain and check the internal packets leaving the
      domain. It does not necessarily mean that a controlled domain is a
      single administrative domain or a single organization. A controlled
      domain can correspond to a single administrative domain or can be
      composed by multiple administrative domains under a defined network
      management. Indeed, some scenarios may imply that the Alternate Marking
      Method involves more than one domain, but in these cases, it is
      RECOMMENDED that the multiple domains create a whole controlled domain
      while traversing the external domain by employing IPsec authentication
      and encryption or other VPN technology that provides full packet
      confidentiality and integrity protection. In a few words, it must be
      possible to control the domain boundaries and eventually use specific
      precautions if the traffic traverse the Internet.</t>

      <t>The Alternate Marking measurement domain can overlap with the
      controlled domain or may be a subset of the controlled domain. The
      typical scenarios for the application of the Alternate Marking Method
      depend on the controlled domain boundaries, in particular:<list>
          <t>the user equipment can be the starting or ending node, only in
          case it is fully managed and if it belongs to the controlled domain.
          In this case the user generated packets contain the Alternate
          Marking data. But, in practice, this is not common due to the fact
          that the user equipment cannot be totally secured in the majority of
          cases.</t>

          <t>the CPE (Customer Premises Equipment) or the PE (Provider Edge)
          routers are most likely to be the starting or ending nodes since
          they can be border routers of the controlled domain. For instance,
          the CPE, which connects the user's premises with the service
          provider's network, belongs to a controlled domain only if it is
          managed by the service provider and if additional security measures
          are taken to keep it trustworthy. Typically the CPE or the PE can
          encapsulate a received packet in an outer header which contains the
          Alternate Marking data. They can also be able to filter and drop
          packets from outside of the domain with inconsistent fields to make
          effective the relevant security rules at the domain boundaries, for
          example a simple security check can be to insert the Alternate
          Marking data if and only if the destination is within the controlled
          domain.</t>
        </list></t>
    </section>

    <section title="Alternate Marking Measurement Nodes">
      <t>An Alternate-Marking Domain consists of marking nodes, unmarking
      nodes, and transit nodes.<list>
          <t>A marking node, also called encapsulating node, incorporates the
          AltMark Data Fields into packets in order to enable
          Alternate-Marking. If the Alternate-Marking method is enabled for a
          selected flow of the traffic, the encapsulating node is responsible
          for applying the AltMark functionality to the selected flow and to
          take initial timestamps and packet counters.</t>

          <t>A transit node only reads AltMark Data Fields in order to take
          timestamps and packet counters.</t>

          <t>An unmarking node, also called decapsulating node, reads AltMark
          Data Fields in order to take final timestamps and packet counters
          and then removes any AltMark Option from packets.</t>
        </list></t>

      <figure title="Roles of Alternate-Marking Nodes">
        <artwork><![CDATA[
          Export of       Export of       Export of      Export of
          AltMark data    AltMark data    AltMark data   AltMark data
              ^               ^               ^               ^
              |               |               |               |
              |               |               |               |
User     +----+----+     +----+----+     +----+----+     +----+----+
packets  |Marking  |     | Transit |     | Transit |     |Unmarking|
-------->|Node     |====>| Node    |====>| Node    |====>|Node     |-->
         |         |     | A       |     | B       |     |         |
         +---------+     +---------+     +---------+     +---------+
]]></artwork>
      </figure>
    </section>

    <section title="Type of Measurements">
      <t>The methodology described in the previous sections can be applied to
      various performance measurement problems. The only requirement is to
      select and mark the flow to be monitored; in this way, packets are
      batched by the sender, and each batch is alternately marked such that it
      can be easily recognized by the receiver.</t>

      <t>Either one or two flag bits might be available for marking in
      different deployments:<list>
          <t>One flag: packet loss measurement MUST be done as described in
          Section 3.1 of <xref target="RFC9341"/>, while delay measurement
          MUST be done according to the single-marking method described in
          Section 3.2.1 of <xref target="RFC9341"/>. Mean delay (Section
          3.2.1.1 of <xref target="RFC9341"/>) MAY also be used but it could
          imply more computational load.</t>

          <t>Two flags: packet loss measurement MUST be done as described in
          Section 3.1 of <xref target="RFC9341"/>, while delay measurement
          MUST be done according to double-marking method Section 3.2.2 of
          <xref target="RFC9341"/>. In this case single-marking MAY also be
          used in combination with double-marking and the two approaches
          provide slightly different pieces of information that can be
          combined to have a more robust data set.</t>
        </list></t>

      <t>There are some operational guidelines to consider for the purpose of
      deciding to follow the recommendations above and use one or two
      flags.<list>
          <t>The Alternate-Marking method utilizes specific flags in the
          packet header, so an important factor is the number of flags
          available for the implementation. Indeed, if there is only one flag
          available there is no other way, while if two flags are available
          the option with two flags is certainly more complete.</t>

          <t>The duration of the Alternate-Marking period affects the
          frequency of the measurement and this is a parameter that can be
          decided on the basis of the required temporal sampling. But it
          cannot be freely chosen, as explained in Section 5 of <xref
          target="RFC9341"/>.</t>

          <t>The Alternate-Marking methodologies enable packet loss, delay and
          delay variation calculation, but in accordance with the method used
          (e.g. single-marking or double-marking), there is different kind of
          information that can be derived. For example, to get more statistics
          of extent data, the option with two flags is desirable. For this
          reason, the type of data needed in the specific scenario is an
          additional element to take into account.</t>

          <t>The Alternate-Marking methods imply different computational load
          depending on the method employed. Therefore, the available
          computational resources on the measurement points can also influence
          the choice. As an example, mean delay calculation may require more
          processing and it may not be the best option to minimize the
          computational load.</t>
        </list></t>

      <t>A deployment of the Alternate-Marking Method should also take into
      account how to handle and recognize marked and unmarked traffic. Since
      Alternate-Marking normally employs a marking field which is dedicated,
      reserved, and included in a protocol extension, the measurement points
      can learn whether the measurement is activated or not by checking if the
      specific extension is included or not within the packets.</t>
    </section>

    <section title="Manageability">
      <t>The YANG model can be used for configuring Alternate-Marking in
      network nodes that support it. An example is defined in <xref
      target="I-D.wang-ippm-alt-mark-yang"/>.</t>

      <t>There are also other control plane mechanisms to advertise and
      activate AltMark capabilities, using PCEP or BGP: <xref
      target="I-D.ietf-idr-sr-policy-ifit"/>, <xref
      target="I-D.ietf-idr-bgp-ifit-capabilities"/>, <xref
      target="I-D.ietf-pce-pcep-ifit"/>.</t>

      <t>These mechanisms can be used to signal and configure the parameters
      to identify the flow to monitor both in case of point-to-point flow and
      multipoint-to-multipoint flow. Indeed, the selection of the
      identification fields directly affects the type of paths that the flow
      would follow in the network. As an example, for IPv6 the setting of the
      Flow Monitoring Identification (FlowMonID) is used in combination with
      source and destination addresses to identify a flow, as described in
      Section 5.3 of <xref target="RFC9343"/>, and it can be algorithmically
      generated by the source node or assigned by the central controller.</t>

      <t>Additionally, other parameters are essential for the activation of
      the AltMark methodology: the choice between end-to-end or hop-by-hop
      measurement, the choice between the methods with one flag or two flags
      and the duration of the Alternate-Marking period which affects the
      measurement frequency (longer the duration of the block, the less
      frequently the measurement can be taken).</t>
    </section>

    <section title="Data Export and Collection">
      <t>Each packet marked for Alternate-Marking, as for example the AltMark
      IPv6 option type defined in Section 3.1 of <xref target="RFC9343"/> or
      the Segment Routing TLV Type as defined in Section 3.1 of <xref
      target="I-D.fz-spring-srv6-alt-mark"/> MUST be copied to the IPFIX or
      YANG push metering process depending which Network Telemetry <xref
      target="RFC9232"/> protocol is used to export the data.</t>

      <figure title="Alternate-Marking Framework with Data Export">
        <artwork><![CDATA[
                                +--------------+
                               +-------------+ |
                               | Network     | |
                               | Data        | |
                               | Collection  |-+
                               +-------------+
                                      ^
                                      |
                                      |
                                      |
              +---------------+-------+-------+---------------+
              |               |               |               |
              |               |               |               |
User     +----+----+     +----+----+     +----+----+     +----+----+
packets  |Marking  |     | Transit |     | Transit |     |Unmarking|
-------->|Node     |====>| Node    |====>| Node    |====>|Node     |-->
         |         |     | A       |     | B       |     |         |
         +---------+     +---------+     +---------+     +---------+

]]></artwork>
      </figure>

      <section title="IPFIX">
        <t>For IPFIX <xref target="RFC7011"/>, the data decomposition can be
        achieved on the Alternate-Marking-aware node exporting the data or on
        the data collection. When decomposed at the data collection, the
        headers, as example the IPv6 options type header described in Section
        3.1 of <xref target="RFC9343"/> or the Segment Routing header TLV as
        described in Section 3.1 of <xref
        target="I-D.fz-spring-srv6-alt-mark"/> containing the FlowMonID, Loss
        and Delay flag are being exposed as part of
        ipPayloadPacketSection(IE314), defined in Section 4.2 of RFC 7133.
        When being decomposed on the Alternate-Marking-aware node, new IPFIX
        entities for FlowMonID, Loss and Delay flag are needed so that the
        data can now be aggregated according to section 5 of <xref
        target="RFC7015"/>. FlowMonID is a Flow Key field. The following IPFIX
        entities are of interest to describe the relationship to the
        forwarding topology and the control-plane.</t>

        <t><list style="symbols">
            <t>node id, ingressInterface(IE10) and egressInterface(IE14)
            describes on which node which logical ingress and egress
            interfaces have been used to forward the packet.</t>

            <t>Node id and egressPhysicalInterface(253) describes on which
            node which physical egress interfaces have been used to forward
            the packet.</t>

            <t>Node id and ipNextHopIPv4Address(IE15) or
            ipNextHopIPv6Address(IE62), describes the forwarding path to which
            next-hop IP address.</t>

            <t>Node id and mplsTopLabelIPv4Address(IE47) or
            srhActiveSegmentIPv6 from <xref
            target="I-D.ietf-opsawg-ipfix-srv6-srh"/> describes the forwarding
            path to which MPLS top label IPv4 address or SRv6 active
            segment.</t>

            <t>BGP communities are often used for setting a path priority or
            service selection. bgpDestinationExtendedCommunityList(488) or
            bgpDestinationCommunityList(485) or
            bgpDestinationLargeCommunityList(491) describes which group of
            prefixes have been used to forward the packet.</t>

            <t>Node id and destinationIPv4Address(13),
            destinationTransportPort(11), protocolIdentifier (4) and
            sourceIPv4Address(IE8) describes the forwarding path on each node
            from each IPv4 source address to a specific application in the
            network.</t>
          </list></t>

        <t>To calculate loss, the packet count with octetDeltaCount(IE1) and
        to calculate delay, either flowStartSeconds(IE150),
        flowStartMilliseconds(IE152), flowStartMicroseconds(IE154) or
        flowStartNanoseconds(IE156), depending on timestamp granularity
        requirements, are needed.</t>

        <t>To calculate loss, the packet count with octetDeltaCount(IE1) and
        to calculate delay, either flowStartSeconds(IE150),
        flowStartMilliseconds(IE152), flowStartMicroseconds(IE154) or
        flowStartNanoseconds(IE156), depending on timestamp granularity
        requirements, are needed.</t>
      </section>

      <section title="YANG Push">
        <t>For YANG Push <xref target="RFC8639"/>, periodical subscription as
        defined in Section 3.1 of <xref target="RFC8641"/> is used to
        subscribe data. Decomposition is done on the Alternate-Marking-aware
        node publishing the data. The YANG module contains FlowMonID as key,
        Loss and Delay flag, ingress and egress interface ifIndex <xref
        target="RFC2863"/>, octet delta count describing the amount of
        observed packets within a flow to measure loss, and flow start
        timestamp describing the first packet observed for measuring delay as
        leafes.</t>

        <t>Since the amount of observed data could overwhelm a route processor
        on a network node, publishing data from network processors as
        specified in <xref target="I-D.ietf-netconf-distributed-notif"/> is
        advised.</t>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section title="Encapsulations">
      <section title="IPv6">
        <t>Alternate-Marking encapsulation for IPv6 is defined in <xref
        target="RFC9343"/>, which also discusses deployment considerations for
        IPv6 networks.</t>

        <t>The <xref target="RFC9343">IPv6 AltMark Option</xref> applies the
        Alternate Marking Method to IPv6, and defines an Extension Header
        Option to encode the Alternate Marking Method for both the Hop-by-Hop
        Options Header and the Destination Options Header.</t>
      </section>

      <section title="SRv6">
        <t>Alternate-Marking encapsulation for SRv6 is discussed in <xref
        target="RFC9343">IPv6 AltMark Option</xref> and <xref
        target="I-D.fz-spring-srv6-alt-mark"/>.</t>
      </section>

      <section title="BIER">
        <t>Alternate-Marking encapsulation for BIER is introduced in <xref
        target="I-D.ietf-bier-pmmm-oam"/>.</t>
      </section>

      <section title="MPLS">
        <t>Alternate-Marking encapsulation for MPLS is introduced in <xref
        target="I-D.ietf-mpls-rfc6374-sfl"/>.</t>
      </section>

      <section title="SFC">
        <t>Alternate-Marking encapsulation for SFC is introduced in <xref
        target="I-D.mfm-ippm-sfc-nsh-pmamm"/>.</t>
      </section>

      <section title="NVO3">
        <t>Alternate-Marking encapsulation for NVO3 is introduced in <xref
        target="I-D.fmm-nvo3-pm-alt-mark"/>.</t>
      </section>

      <section title="Enhanced capabilities">
        <t><xref target="I-D.zhou-ippm-enhanced-alternate-marking"/> defines
        extended data fields for the AltMark Option and provides enhanced
        capabilities to overcome some challenges and enable future proof
        applications.</t>

        <t>It is worth mentioning that the enhanced capabilities are intended
        for further use and are optional.</t>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section title="Implementation Considerations">
      <t>In a controlled domain, the nodes may support the AltMark specific
      encapsulation and this also depends on the implementation. If a node is
      configured to read the AltMark option, the measurement is done on that
      node, otherwise it is simply not considered in the measurement.</t>

      <t>Assuming that the measurement domain overlaps with the controlled
      domain, the procedure for AltMark data encapsulation can be summarized
      as follows: <list style="symbols">
          <t>Ingress Node: the Ingress Node of a controlled domain that
          supports the Alternate Marking Method adds the AltMark data in the
          the data packets.</t>

          <t>Intermediate Node: if an Intermediate Node is not capable of
          processing the AltMark data, it simply ignores it. If an
          Intermediate Node is capable of processing the AltMark data, it
          processes it.</t>

          <t>Egress SR Node: The Egress Node is the last node of the
          controlled domain. The processing if the AltMark data is similar to
          the processing at the Intermediate Nodes. The only difference is
          that it needs to remove the AltMark data from the the data
          packets.</t>
        </list></t>
    </section>

    <section anchor="Security" title="Security Considerations">
      <t><xref target="RFC9341">Alternate Marking</xref> and <xref
      target="RFC9342">Multipoint Alternate Marking</xref> analyze different
      security concerns and related solutions. These aspects are valid and
      applicable also to this document. In particular the fundamental security
      requirement is that Alternate Marking MUST only be applied in a specific
      limited domain, as also mentioned in <xref target="RFC8799"/>.</t>
    </section>

    <section anchor="IANA" title="IANA Considerations">
      <t>This document has no request to IANA.</t>
    </section>

    <section anchor="Acknowledgements" title="Acknowledgements">
      <t>TBD</t>
    </section>
  </middle>

  <back>
    <references title="Normative References">
      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.2119'?>

      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.8174'?>

      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.9341'?>

      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.9342'?>

      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.9343'?>
    </references>

    <references title="Informative References">
      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.2863'?>

      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.7011'?>

      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.7015'?>

      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.8321'?>

      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.8889'?>

      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.7799'?>

      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.8799'?>

      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.8639'?>

      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.8641'?>

      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.9232'?>

      <?rfc include='reference.I-D.zhou-ippm-enhanced-alternate-marking'?>

      <?rfc include='reference.I-D.ietf-idr-sr-policy-ifit'?>

      <?rfc include='reference.I-D.ietf-idr-bgp-ifit-capabilities'?>

      <?rfc include='reference.I-D.ietf-pce-pcep-ifit'?>

      <?rfc include='reference.I-D.wang-ippm-alt-mark-yang'?>

      <?rfc include='reference.I-D.fz-spring-srv6-alt-mark'?>

      <?rfc include='reference.I-D.ietf-bier-pmmm-oam'?>

      <?rfc include='reference.I-D.ietf-mpls-rfc6374-sfl'?>

      <?rfc include='reference.I-D.mfm-ippm-sfc-nsh-pmamm'?>

      <?rfc include='reference.I-D.fmm-nvo3-pm-alt-mark'?>

      <?rfc include='reference.I-D.ietf-opsawg-ipfix-srv6-srh'?>

      <?rfc include='reference.I-D.ietf-netconf-distributed-notif'?>
    </references>
  </back>
</rfc>
